A Guide to the Gaines Family Papers, 1766-1905
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Gaines Family Papers, 1766-1905
The Library of Virginia
24417
65 leaves and 28 pages
Gaines Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 3 January 1956 from Mrs. Ormonde Smith, Petersburg, Virginia.
Biographical Information
The Gaines family was a prominent family in Charlotte, Hanover, King and Queen, and King William Counties, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1766-1905, of the Gaines family of Charlotte County, Virginia, consisting of wills from King William and King and Queen Counties, Virginia; a deed from Hanover County, Virginia; announcement for medical lectures by Charles Bell Gibson; stock certificate for the Marysville Plank Road in Charlotte and Campbell Counties, Virginia; a deposition from Hanover County; correspondence of the Gaines family of Charlotte County and Richmond, Virginia, during the Civil War; correspondence from Joseph E. Johnston to William Gaines concerning the elections of 1878; and a circular letter regarding Company B, 14th Virginia Cavalry. Collection also contains judicial records from the Chancery District Court in Williamsburg, Virginia for Garlick et al v Pollard et al. Also contains genealogical notes on the Camm and Garlick families of King William and King and Queen Counties. Also includes a letter by Colonel Norman Smith of the 13th New Hampshire Infantry, and maps of the battle fields of Cold Harbor, Fredericksburg, Getty's Station, and Fort Harrison.
Contents List
- Will, 31 October 1766, of Harry Gains [Gaines] of King William County, Virginia.
- Will, 14 July 1765 and recorded 16 October 1772, of Samuel Garlick of King William County.
- Court records, ca. 1810, in suit of Garlick et al v Pollard et al regarding the estate of Camm Garlick (d. 1782) in the Chancery District Court of Williamsburg, Virginia.
- Deed, 13 October 1821 and recorded 24 October 1821, for 48 acres in Hanover County, Virginia, from Isham A. King and Hannah King to James Govan of Hanover County.
- Will, 28 July 1848, codicil 29 July 1848, and recorded 9 October 1848, of John Gaines of King and Queen County, Virginia.
- Announcement from the medical department of Hampden Sidney College for lectures on surgery and surgical anatomy by Charles Bell Gibson, M.D. during the 1849-1850 session.
- Stock certificate, 20 October 1854, for two shares of the Marysville Plank Road Company.
- Letter, 27 August 1862, from R. F. Gaines in Botetourt County, Virginia, to his wife stating that he will be trying the springs at Coyner's Springs and then return home.
- Deposition, 31 January 1863, of William F. Gaines of Hanover County regarding confiscation of property by the Union army in 1862.
- Letter, 17 July 1863, from R. J. Gaines of Charlotte County to Sallie [Sarah] Gaines regarding her living near the enemy and the losses Confederate armies have suffered.
- Letter, 1 September 1863, from R. J. Gaines to William Gaines informing William that there is a place for rent in Charlotte County and providing some family news.
- Letter, 31 October 1863, from Normand Smith of 13th New Hampshire Infantry to his parents discussing the new conscripts in his regiment and describing his quarters and camp life.
- Letter, 8 March 1865, from Richard V. Gaines to his brother regarding the military situation around Richmond and Petersburg, Virginia.
- Letter, 11 March 1865, from Robert H. Gaines of the 14th Virginia Cavalry in Sussex County, Virginia, to his brother stating that Markham Eggleston is going to run for office in Charlotte County and describing their camp.
- Parole, 25 May 1865, of William Gaines of Company I, 15th Virginia Infantry.
- Letter, 5 December 1865, from Robert H. Gaines of Charlotte County to William Gaines of Richmond concerning killing of hogs and other matters.
- Letter, 27 February 1866, from Richard V. Gaines in Alabama to his brother describing post-war conditions in Alabama.
- Letter, 10 August 1878, from Joseph E. Johnston to William Gaines, both of Richmond regarding the upcoming primary elections.
- Letter, 30 July 1878, from Joseph E. Johnston to William Gaines, both of Richmond concerning the committees for the primary elections.
- Circular letter, 25 July 1905, from E. E. Bouldin of Danville, Virginia, to his former company, Company B, 14th Virginia Cavalry, sending a list of battles the company fought in and containing the wounded at each fight and asking for corrections and additions, the list was created by Samuel M. Gaines of Washington D.C.
- Genealogical notes on the Camm and Garlick families of King and Queen County, including the will, 17 March 1766 and codicil 20 February 1767, of John Camm, and correspondence from Samuel Garlick to Robert Hill, both of King and Queen County.
- Maps of Cold Harbor, Getty's Station, Fredericksburg, and Fort Harrison drawn by Colonel Normand Smith.